<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Activities on Baltic Security Foundation</title>
    <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/categories/activities/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Activities on Baltic Security Foundation</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://balticsecurity.eu/categories/activities/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Continued support to Ukrainians</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/ukraine_support/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/ukraine_support/</guid>
      <description>The Baltic Security Foundation continues to support Ukrainian refugees in Latvia and the civilians in Ukraine. First of all, our team member Andreis Purim has been personally involved to facilitate the delivery of humanitarian aid to Lviv, Ukraine.
Furthermore, since summer of 2022, the Baltic Security Foundation has gathered support from the U.S. Embassy in Latvia and many non-governmental organizations and individual supporters to provide free English classes for the Ukrainian refugees who have fled the Russian aggression.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BSF at the U.S. Congress</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/us_congress/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/us_congress/</guid>
      <description>The Baltic Security Foundation co-hosted an event at the Congress of the United States of America on China&amp;rsquo;s influence in the Baltic Sea region. The event was made possible together with The Jamestown Foundation and JBANC. The event was opened by co-chair of the House Baltic Caucus Representative Don Bacon.
In the first part of the event, Glen E. Howard, Roger W. Robinson Jr., Olevs Nikers and Dimon Liu discussed the book “Between Brussels and Beijing: Transatlantic Response to Chinese Presence in the Baltic Sea.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New book published: Between Brussels and Beijing: The Transatlantic Response to the Chinese Presence in the Baltic Sea Region</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/between_brussels_and_beijing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/between_brussels_and_beijing/</guid>
      <description>Read online at the Jamestown Foundation Website! Between Brussels and Beijing: The Transatlantic Response to the Chinese Presence in the Baltic Sea Region serves as a comprehensive analysis of China’s presence in the Baltic Sea littoral countries and subsequently related developments in the domains of education, finance and infrastructure.
Scholars Olevs Nikers and Otto Tabuns together with their Baltic Security Foundation team and other regional and international experts provide a set of in-depth national case studies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Luncheon with the President of the Baltic Security Foundation at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy, Tufts University</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/fletcher_luncheon/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/fletcher_luncheon/</guid>
      <description>On November 17 Olevs Nikers, President of the Baltic Security Foundation visited affiliates of the Russia and Eurasia Program at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy at Tufts University. A special luncheon gathered students and professors of this program to discuss the global security situation, Russia&amp;rsquo;s war against Ukraine and its implications for Baltic Security, as well as Chinese presence in the Baltic Sea Region. Special interest from the side of the students was expressed in the Transatlantic Security Exchange, using the opportunity to familiarize themselves with the details of this exchange, organized by the Baltic Security Foundation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>University Book Donation</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/book_exchange/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/book_exchange/</guid>
      <description>The Baltic Security Foundation team shares their most recent books to universities around the world to promote the studies of regional security. The BSF president Mr. Olevs Nikers visited the University of Washington and donated copies of &amp;ldquo;Baltic Sea Security: Regional and Sectoral Perspectives&amp;rdquo; to the UW University Libraries. The BSF team looks forward to these books being useful for the university, especially for its renown Baltic Studies program.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baltic Cyber Resilience Report Published</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/baltic-cyber-resilience-report/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/baltic-cyber-resilience-report/</guid>
      <description>Baltic Security Foundation is proud to announce the publication of the Baltic Cyber Resilience Report. This report includes the assessment of cybersecurity issues in the three Baltic states, looking at the most important regional, bilateral and multilateral levels. This publication was made possible with the support of Microsoft NV and Mr. Uldis Šalajevs.
To access the full report, click here</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baltic Sea Security Initiative Report Published by Jamestown Foundation</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/baltic-sea-security-initiative-report/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/baltic-sea-security-initiative-report/</guid>
      <description>Baltic Security Foundation is proud to annouce the publication of the Baltic Sea Security Initiative Report in conjunction with the Jamestown Foundation (Washington, D.C.). The report is the product of cooperative research conducted between 2019-2020 with a number of regional security experts from throughout the Baltic Sea Region, providing both assessments and recommendations for policy makers in the fields of defense and deterrence, societal security, energy security, and more. Click the link below to access the full report.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baltic Fund</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/baltic_fund/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/baltic_fund/</guid>
      <description>On November 28, 2019, Baltic Security Foundation team participated in the NATO Eastern Flank Security conference, hosted by Warsaw Institute. Following a keynote speech by Piotr Naimski, Secretary of State in the Chancellery of the Prime Minister of Poland, Government Plenipotentiary for Strategic Energy Infrastructure, Mr Olevs Nikers spoke at the panel on energy security, covering political and economic issues of nuclear power and natural gas, while Mr Otto Tabuns gave his views on intraregional and European challenges for Baltic security at the discussion on defence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baltic Sea Security Initiative</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/baltic_sea_security_initiative/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/baltic_sea_security_initiative/</guid>
      <description>BSSI gathers Baltic Sea region experts to assess and recommend better solutions in the fields of defence, societal security, economic security and cybersecurity. The experts look at what the countries of Northern, Eastern and Central Europe can do more efficiently together to achieve stronger regional security. The initiative consists of eight workshops in the Baltic Sea countries (Estonia, Latvia, Lithuania, Poland, Germany, Denmark etc.). The main conclusions of the initiative will be publicly presented and discussed in a conference in Helsinki, Finland in the Spring 2020.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baltic Security Foundation Team Activities in November 2019</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/november_activities/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/november_activities/</guid>
      <description>This month the Baltic Security Foundation team has been very active on both sides of the Atlantic Ocean, continuing existing projects and pursuing new areas of cooperation with likeminded experts and stakeholders.
On November 8, the Foundation team participated in the second annual Baltic Advocacy Day in Washington D.C., as well as the 13th annual Baltic Conference organized by the Joint Baltic American National Committee that represents major Baltic-American organizations. This gave an opportunity to speak with members of several offices of U.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regional Activities 2019</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/regional_activities/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/regional_activities/</guid>
      <description>October 2019 has been busy for the Baltic Security Foundation, pursuing our goal of fostering and promoting Baltic defense and security. The team has both participated in and organized events covering regional security issues.
The Rīga Conference 2019 took place on October 11th and 12th. Mr. Olevs Nikers and Mr. Otto Tabuns were both invited to participate. The agenda included current challenges, such as the issue of EU and NATO identities as well as understanding European strategic autonomy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baltic Security Foundation Presents at the ECPR General Conference in Wrocław</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/wroclaw_conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/wroclaw_conference/</guid>
      <description>BSF President Mr. Olevs Nikers and BSF Director Mr. Otto Tabuns took part in the panel “Addressing Security Challenges in the Baltic Region through Multilateral Cooperation” of the European Consortium for Political Research (ECPR) 13th General Conference September 5, 2019 in Wrocław, Poland.
During his presentation “Sub-Regional Defense Synchronization – Theory Perspectives and Security Expectations for the Baltics,” Mr. Nikers outlined and discussed the origin and sustainability of the modern security alliance between small countries.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
