<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>China on Baltic Security Foundation</title>
    <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/tags/china/</link>
    <description>Recent content in China on Baltic Security Foundation</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://balticsecurity.eu/tags/china/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>New book published: Between Brussels and Beijing: The Transatlantic Response to the Chinese Presence in the Baltic Sea Region</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/between_brussels_and_beijing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/between_brussels_and_beijing/</guid>
      <description>Read online at the Jamestown Foundation Website! Between Brussels and Beijing: The Transatlantic Response to the Chinese Presence in the Baltic Sea Region serves as a comprehensive analysis of China’s presence in the Baltic Sea littoral countries and subsequently related developments in the domains of education, finance and infrastructure.
Scholars Olevs Nikers and Otto Tabuns together with their Baltic Security Foundation team and other regional and international experts provide a set of in-depth national case studies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transatlantic response to China</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/transatlantic_response_to_china/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/transatlantic_response_to_china/</guid>
      <description>Roger W. Robinson Jr. speaks on the Transatlantic response to China, importance of the capital markets, and the international security context relevant to the Baltic Sea region.
This address is part of the Baltic Sea Security Conference 2022: Transatlantic Response to China&amp;rsquo;s Presence in the Baltic Sea Region. The conference was hosted by the Baltic Security Foundation at the Hotel Kempinski Adlon in Berlin on August 17, 2022.
The conference showcased the research on China&amp;rsquo;s presence in the Baltic Sea region domains of finance, education and infrastructure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baltic Sea Security Conference 2022</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/baltic_sea_security_conference_2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/baltic_sea_security_conference_2022/</guid>
      <description>Transatlantic response to China’s presence in the Baltic Sea Region
The Euroatlantic states sharing the Baltic Sea have been subject to persistent security threats that have made them seek international solutions to maintain peace and stability. Challenges associated with Russia have been at the forefront for decades and are so today with its war against Ukraine. Meanwhile over the last decade the regional presence of China has increased - welcomed by many but analyzed by few.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
