<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Matthew Thomas on Baltic Security Foundation</title>
    <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/authors/matthew-thomas/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Matthew Thomas on Baltic Security Foundation</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://balticsecurity.eu/authors/matthew-thomas/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Lithuania-Kaliningrad Transit Row: A Broader EU and NATO Perspective</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/lithuania_kaliningrad/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/lithuania_kaliningrad/</guid>
      <description>Through much of the end of June, Lithuania has been embroiled in a row with Russia over the implementation of EU sanctions on certain kinds of goods in transit between Russia and its Kaliningrad exclave. Russia has claimed that Lithuania’s actions are a “violation of everything,” and has promised a response that is “not diplomatic.” In turn, Lithuania has argued that it is simply putting into practice the EU sanctions regime agreed upon as early as March, and that contrary to Russian claims, its actions will not halt all transit between Russia and Kaliningrad; rather, it will only stop the flow of sanctioned goods.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Major Russian Invasion of Ukraine Imminent</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/major_russian_invasion_of_ukraine_imminent/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/major_russian_invasion_of_ukraine_imminent/</guid>
      <description>Russia will invade Ukraine. It is no longer a matter of if, but when. Some pundits have been quick to point out that Russia already invaded Ukraine in 2014 and has been an occupier since then. This is true, but short of inventing some other barbarically cumbersome turn of phrase or vague milquetoast nonsense that fails to capture the urgency of the situation, an invasion is perhaps the best word available to describe what is on the horizon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Russia Testing Western Resolve: How will the West Respond?</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/russia_testing_western_resolve/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/russia_testing_western_resolve/</guid>
      <description>From the Baltics, to Poland, to Ukraine, and even outer space, Russia has recently been testing Western resolve on numerous fronts. Perhaps most pressing of the myriad issues in recent news are the recent Russian military buildup around Ukraine and Belarus’ exploitation (with at least tacit Russian support) of migrants from the Middle East to wage hybrid war on Poland, Latvia, and Lithuania. Moving forward, how the West responds to these issues will play a major role in Russia’s course of action.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estonia’s New Anti-Ship Missiles: Crucial Naval Capability and Overdue Strategic Shift to Sea</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/estonia_new_anti-ship_missile/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/estonia_new_anti-ship_missile/</guid>
      <description>Earlier this month, the Estonian Center for Defense Investment (ECDI) announced the purchase of Blue Spear 5G SSM land-to-sea missile systems from Israel. With a maximum range of 290 kilometers (approximately 180.2 miles), the Blue Spear missile system can reach targets across both the Gulf of Finland and the Baltic Sea, and can also be used to strike both moving and stationary targets at sea in all weather conditions, day or night.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zapad 2021: Spotlight on Belarus</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/zapad_2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/zapad_2021/</guid>
      <description>For international observers, military exercises are a key litmus test of a country’s strengths and weaknesses. Likewise, they reflect that country’s view to the strategies of its supposed opponents. In that sense, this year’s Zapad (“West”) exercises conducted in Russia and Belarus were no different. They revealed Russia’s perceptions of the way the NATO will fight, given the still relatively unlikely event of war between the two. Likewise, the exercises remained highly scripted as in the past, and the scenarios involved were largely the same.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Belarusian Migrant Crisis in Broader Geopolitical Context</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/belarusian_migrant_crisis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/belarusian_migrant_crisis/</guid>
      <description>For about the last two months, Lithuania has been in the throes of a migration crisis like it has never seen before. In retaliation to the sanctions placed on his regime following the forced grounding of a passenger airliner to arrest journalist Roman Protasevich, Belarusian President Aleksandr Lukashenka promised to force Europe (and in particular, Lithuania) to deal with drug smuggling and migrant flows on their own. Aside from Lukashenka’s claim to have been stopping migrants and smugglers in the past, the statement gives clear indication of intent to weaponize migration and the flow of contraband.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NATO Summit 2021: Broad Goals, Few Specifics</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/nato_summit_2021_broad_goals_few_specifics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/nato_summit_2021_broad_goals_few_specifics/</guid>
      <description>On June 14, heads of state from all NATO members met in Brussels for the 2021 NATO summit. This occurred smack in the middle of U.S. President Biden’s much touted trip to Europe, and overall received little media attention. A Google search of the summit produces primarily NATO press releases, the odd news article here or there (but only from mainstream yet highly partisan sources, fringe outlets, and little else), few analyses, and a preponderance of pre-summit anticipatory articles from news sources and think tanks alike.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Securing Energy Supply in the Baltics</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/securing_energy_supply_baltics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/securing_energy_supply_baltics/</guid>
      <description>This month, Lithuania announced the arrival of a 164-tonne transformer as part of the ongoing process for synchronization with the Continental European power grid. This step is considered crucial for successfully exiting the Soviet era BRELL agreement, in which the Baltics’ power grids are controlled by Moscow. Exiting BRELL is a major component of the Baltics’ overall strategy not only for energy security, but for their national security broadly.
Under the BRELL agreement, the Baltics have been synchronously connected to the Integrated Power System/United Power System (IPS/UPS) grid with Russia and Belarus since the end of the Soviet period.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ukraine in the Balance. Again.</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/ukraine_in_the_balance/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/ukraine_in_the_balance/</guid>
      <description>Once again, Ukraine faces the threat of Russian aggression. Surrounded on nearly all sides, it faces a potential crisis of existence, as Moscow sees an opportunity to take on yet more ambitious objectives against its hapless neighbor. Unfortunately for Ukraine, nothing guarantees its security, and it is grossly, obscenely outmatched by its adversary. What exactly Russia intends to do remains a mystery, but one thing is clear: Russia plans to attack Ukraine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>U.S. Perspectives on Nord Stream 2</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/perspectives_nord_stream2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/perspectives_nord_stream2/</guid>
      <description>U.S. President Joe Biden has claimed that Nord Stream 2, the controversial Russo-German pipeline project, is a “bad deal for Europe” and has stated his administration’s opposition to the project. At face value, that would appear to be a rare continuity with the previous administration, but a deeper dive into the various perspectives in Washington reveals a much more complicated position. Despite spoken commitments to the bipartisan sanctions regime instituted by the Trump administration, it appears that the Biden administration is ready to wash its hands of the issue and move on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Contrarian View of Joe Biden and NATO</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/contrarian_view_biden_nato/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/contrarian_view_biden_nato/</guid>
      <description>In the world of analysis, contrarian viewpoints are equally disliked and necessary. They help shape a more robust understanding of the situation at hand and can prepare countries for the otherwise unexpected. As much of Europe celebrates Joe Biden taking the helm in the United States after the much despised Trump administration, it is worthwhile to take a step back and question whether or not that enthusiasm is really merited. As such, this paper puts forth an unabashedly contrarian viewpoint for the sake of an enriched understanding of the world as it may be going forward, lest the Baltics be caught off guard in the broader optimism of their European counterparts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>U.S.-Poland Enhanced Defense Cooperation Agreement and Why It Matters</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/u.s._poland_edca/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/u.s._poland_edca/</guid>
      <description>On November 9, 2020, 31 years after the fall of the Berlin Wall, Polish President Andrzej Duda signed the Polish Senate’s ratification bill of the U.S.-Polish Enhanced Defense Cooperation Agreement (EDCA). This agreement contains a number of provisions that will facilitate greater defense cooperation between the United States and Poland and improve deterrence and battle readiness for NATO along the alliance’s Eastern Flank. For the Baltics, this ratification is welcome news, as it not only improves the regional deterrent posture, but also a number of crucial conditions in Poland to enable more rapid and effective defense in the event of Russian aggression on their territory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Much Ado About Something: 2% Defense Expenditures and What Really Matters</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/much_ado_about_something/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/much_ado_about_something/</guid>
      <description>In 2014, NATO member states agreed to target defense expenditures of two percent of gross domestic product (GDP) by 2024. After this commitment, and following Russian aggression in Ukraine, NATO turned the corner on its declining defense expenditures. Facing a new challenge in a revisionist Russia, many allies to the east felt a new sense of urgency about funding their defense, aiming to build a credible deterrent against aggression on their own territory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>As Belarus Descends into Turmoil, the West Should Bolster its Readiness</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/as_belarus_descends/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/as_belarus_descends/</guid>
      <description>Belarus seldom registers in the international press during normal times, but while years like 2020 are not so unprecedented, this certainly is not a normal year. Since President Aleksandr Lukashenko was declared the winner of the fraudulent presidential elections on August 9, the country has spiraled into civil unrest and authoritarian repression, and the headlines keep coming like a stampede. While no one was surprised by the announced outcome of the election, most analysts would not have predicted that Belarus would be launched headlong into a persistent crisis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trust, but Deter: How to Ensure Security Despite Russian Treaty Violations</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/trust_but_deter/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/trust_but_deter/</guid>
      <description>In August, Latvia marked the 100th anniversary of the Latvian-Soviet Peace Treaty, otherwise known as the Treaty of Rīga, which ended Latvia’s War for Independence and marked the beginning of the interwar period for the new Latvian Republic. The treaty established Latvia’s sovereignty and Soviet Russia recognized Latvia’s independence as “inviolable” for all time. But the Soviet Union did not honor this treaty, nor its treaties with Estonia and Lithuania. Between these treaties and other, more modern treaties such as the Intermediate-Range Nuclear Forces (INF) Treaty, we can see that Russia only abides by the treaties it signs for as long as it is convenient, then breaks them when it seems it can get away with doing so.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moving the Front Lines: Could Recent Moves in Europe Signal an Adjustment of U.S. Focus Eastward?</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/moving_the_front_lines/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/moving_the_front_lines/</guid>
      <description>In June the Trump administration announced its decision to pull 9,500 U.S. troops from Germany. The move was lambasted by those on the left and right alike, and indeed, at face value, it appeared counterintuitive. Any return to the Obama and Bush-era troop drawdown in Europe would be foolish facing a revisionist Russia. But if there is anything the keen and impartial observer should know by now about this administration, it is that it keeps its cards close to the chest, absorbing the criticism that inevitably comes and only revealing its end game down the line.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Military Exercises in Kaliningrad Highlight Maritime Threats</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/military_exercises_in_kaliningrad_highlight_maritime_threats/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/military_exercises_in_kaliningrad_highlight_maritime_threats/</guid>
      <description>For eight or nine days beginning on April 20th, around the same time that NATO and Estonian forces were holding the Spring Storm Exercises, Russia held exercises of its own in the Kaliningrad Oblast’. Though not as grandiose in scale as a May 3rd article in Izvestia would suggest, the exercises do demonstrate that Russia is working to practice its maritime capabilities. The main events of the exercises centered around what may have been two amphibious landing drills and also featured anti-aircraft and anti-submarine drills, simulated naval missile attacks, simulated aerial attacks on naval vessels, and mine-laying and mine-clearing exercises.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spring Storm Exercises Demonstrate Ongoing Commitment to Deterrence, Readiness</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/spring_storm/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/spring_storm/</guid>
      <description>Each year, Estonia hosts Spring Storm (Kevadtorm), bringing together forces from all across NATO to conduct field and live-fire exercises. Though smaller in scale and participation due to the coronavirus pandemic, this year’s exercises concluded successfully last week. Spring Storm demonstrates Estonia and its allies’ commitment to ensuring readiness in case of attack, contributing to the credibility of NATO’s deterrence posture on the Eastern Flank.
Military exercises are crucial for training and readiness purposes, as new conscripts/recruits and reservists have an opportunity to train alongside active duty personnel.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Javelin Deliveries and the Prospects of Tank Warfare in the Baltics</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/tank_warfare_baltics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/tank_warfare_baltics/</guid>
      <description>At the beginning of this month, the U.S. delivered 128 javelin anti-tank missiles to Estonia, part of ongoing cooperation between the two countries. This will provide another moderate boost to the credibility of Estonia’s deterrent posture. These kinds of smaller procurements are an important part of the broader effort to build up a credible defense in case of Russian aggression and to signal that the risk outweighs the reward for attacking the Baltic States.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Three Seas Initiative</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/three_seas_initiative/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/three_seas_initiative/</guid>
      <description>Last month, U.S. Secretary of State Mike Pompeo announced that the United States would commit up to $1 Billion in support for the Three Seas Initiative. In so doing, Congress and the administration are providing much needed assistance toward developing the economic and security infrastructure in Central and Eastern Europe. This initiative, launched in 2015 by the Polish and Croatian presidents, aims to make Central Europe a “backbone of European resilience,” in the words of Croatian President Kolinda Grabar-Kitarović.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interoperability at Sea: Sweden and Finland</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/finland_sweden_naval_cooperation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/finland_sweden_naval_cooperation/</guid>
      <description>Last week, Finland and Sweden conducted naval cooperation exercises in the Baltic Sea. Given that these two countries have a long tradition of close cooperation in military affairs, this seems fairly mundane. But these exercises were highly unusual, as Finland’s FNS Uusimaa took orders from Swedish naval command, and Sweden’s HMS Helsingborg received orders from Finland’s command center in Turku. This was the first time in the history of Finnish-Swedish naval cooperation that ships took orders from the opposite country’s command.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Defending the Suwałki Gap</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/defending_suwalki_gap/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/defending_suwalki_gap/</guid>
      <description>At the end of last month, Lithuania and Poland announced that the two countries would each assign a brigade to NATO Headquarters in Poland to “train and act together” for the defense of the Suwałki Gap. According to the signed act of affiliation, Lithuania’s Iron Wolf Mechanized Brigade and Poland’s 15th Mechanized Brigade will train jointly to prepare for operations in the Gap, though they will remain under their own national command.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Belarus: An Overlooked Key to Baltic Security</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/belarus_an_overlooked_key/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/belarus_an_overlooked_key/</guid>
      <description>Winston Churchill once famously quipped that “Russia is a riddle wrapped in a mystery inside an enigma”. A keen observer will notice that Alyaksandar Lukashenka’s Belarus is much the same. All too often, Western analysts have made the mistake of grossly oversimplifying Belarus’ relationship with Russia, as well as its domestic political affairs and broader foreign policy. This has led the West to neglect relations with Minsk, where despite a less than ideal government, great strategic opportunity lies, and where there is also significant strategic risk.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Stopping Nord Stream 2 Matters for the Baltics</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/stopping_nord_stream/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/stopping_nord_stream/</guid>
      <description>Nord Stream 2 is a Russian gas pipeline project running mostly parallel to the current Nord Stream pipeline from Vyborg to Greifswald, Germany. This second line would allow for additional gas flows directly from Russia to Western Europe up to a potential 110 billion cubic meters annually. At face value, this expansion is an economic opportunity that makes sense for Germany and other potential Western European customers. In a perfect world, it would be just that.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improving the Baltic States’ Maritime Security</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/improving_maritime_security/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/improving_maritime_security/</guid>
      <description>Maritime operations have once again been a major theme of recent headlines in Estonia, Latvia, and Lithuania. Following the NATO BALTOPS exercises this summer, repeated violations of the Baltic States’ airspace by Russia, and observing current combat diving operations in Tallinn Bay, maritime security issues are particularly relevant. Unfortunately, given the long-standing emphasis on land-based deterrence, the maritime domain has largely been neglected.
BALTOPS 2019 revealed a key weakness for naval operations: the shallow and largely unmarked coastline hampered amphibious landing operations in Lithuania.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is Baltic Security Important for the U.S., NATO, and Europe? Absolutely!</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/is_baltic_security_important/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/is_baltic_security_important/</guid>
      <description>The three Baltic States are key members of the NATO defensive alliance. Since regaining independence after the illegal Soviet occupation, Latvia, Lithuania, and Estonia have all become deeply integrated into Western institutions, such as NATO and the EU. These small countries, understanding the potential peril of reoccupation by a resurgent Russia after the annexation of Crimea, have been extremely vocal in sounding the alarm that Russia remains a security threat. They understand that the West must get serious about security lest its more vulnerable members once more get trampled.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
