<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Transatlantic on Baltic Security Foundation</title>
    <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/tags/transatlantic/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Transatlantic on Baltic Security Foundation</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://balticsecurity.eu/tags/transatlantic/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>BSF at the U.S. Congress</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/us_congress/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/us_congress/</guid>
      <description>The Baltic Security Foundation co-hosted an event at the Congress of the United States of America on China&amp;rsquo;s influence in the Baltic Sea region. The event was made possible together with The Jamestown Foundation and JBANC. The event was opened by co-chair of the House Baltic Caucus Representative Don Bacon.
In the first part of the event, Glen E. Howard, Roger W. Robinson Jr., Olevs Nikers and Dimon Liu discussed the book “Between Brussels and Beijing: Transatlantic Response to Chinese Presence in the Baltic Sea.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New book published: Between Brussels and Beijing: The Transatlantic Response to the Chinese Presence in the Baltic Sea Region</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/between_brussels_and_beijing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/between_brussels_and_beijing/</guid>
      <description>Read online at the Jamestown Foundation Website! Between Brussels and Beijing: The Transatlantic Response to the Chinese Presence in the Baltic Sea Region serves as a comprehensive analysis of China’s presence in the Baltic Sea littoral countries and subsequently related developments in the domains of education, finance and infrastructure.
Scholars Olevs Nikers and Otto Tabuns together with their Baltic Security Foundation team and other regional and international experts provide a set of in-depth national case studies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Luncheon with the President of the Baltic Security Foundation at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy, Tufts University</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/fletcher_luncheon/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/fletcher_luncheon/</guid>
      <description>On November 17 Olevs Nikers, President of the Baltic Security Foundation visited affiliates of the Russia and Eurasia Program at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy at Tufts University. A special luncheon gathered students and professors of this program to discuss the global security situation, Russia&amp;rsquo;s war against Ukraine and its implications for Baltic Security, as well as Chinese presence in the Baltic Sea Region. Special interest from the side of the students was expressed in the Transatlantic Security Exchange, using the opportunity to familiarize themselves with the details of this exchange, organized by the Baltic Security Foundation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transatlantic Security Exchange 2022</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/transatlantic_security_exchange_2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/transatlantic_security_exchange_2022/</guid>
      <description>On October 6, 2022, the State Secretary of Latvian Ministry of Defense Jānis Garisons visited the Bush School of Government and Public Service at Texas A&amp;amp;M and met with Professor Gabriela Marin Thornton and her students who research Baltic security in their capstone course. The capstone course participants partner with the Baltic Security Foundation to propose ways to increase Baltic resilience with a focus on Latvia. The meeting presented an opportunity to discuss the preliminary findings and compare the perspectives on the most important regional security issues in the Baltic Sea Region.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transatlantic response to China</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/transatlantic_response_to_china/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/transatlantic_response_to_china/</guid>
      <description>Roger W. Robinson Jr. speaks on the Transatlantic response to China, importance of the capital markets, and the international security context relevant to the Baltic Sea region.
This address is part of the Baltic Sea Security Conference 2022: Transatlantic Response to China&amp;rsquo;s Presence in the Baltic Sea Region. The conference was hosted by the Baltic Security Foundation at the Hotel Kempinski Adlon in Berlin on August 17, 2022.
The conference showcased the research on China&amp;rsquo;s presence in the Baltic Sea region domains of finance, education and infrastructure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transatlantic Security Exchange</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/transatlantic_security_exchange/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/transatlantic_security_exchange/</guid>
      <description>The Baltic Security Foundation has launched the Transatlantic Security Exchange. The program brings together experts and researchers from Europe and America to focus on further studies of Baltic security in regional and international context.
This week, the BSF team welcomed Rebekkah Chatham and Travis Andrews from the Texas A&amp;amp;M University Bush School of Government &amp;amp; Public Service who will visit several Baltic Sea states for their research on NATO, influence of Russia and China in Europe, regional military cooperation and food security.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>University Book Donation</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/book_exchange/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/book_exchange/</guid>
      <description>The Baltic Security Foundation team shares their most recent books to universities around the world to promote the studies of regional security. The BSF president Mr. Olevs Nikers visited the University of Washington and donated copies of &amp;ldquo;Baltic Sea Security: Regional and Sectoral Perspectives&amp;rdquo; to the UW University Libraries. The BSF team looks forward to these books being useful for the university, especially for its renown Baltic Studies program.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Contrarian View of Joe Biden and NATO</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/contrarian_view_biden_nato/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/contrarian_view_biden_nato/</guid>
      <description>In the world of analysis, contrarian viewpoints are equally disliked and necessary. They help shape a more robust understanding of the situation at hand and can prepare countries for the otherwise unexpected. As much of Europe celebrates Joe Biden taking the helm in the United States after the much despised Trump administration, it is worthwhile to take a step back and question whether or not that enthusiasm is really merited. As such, this paper puts forth an unabashedly contrarian viewpoint for the sake of an enriched understanding of the world as it may be going forward, lest the Baltics be caught off guard in the broader optimism of their European counterparts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>U.S.-Poland Enhanced Defense Cooperation Agreement and Why It Matters</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/u.s._poland_edca/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/u.s._poland_edca/</guid>
      <description>On November 9, 2020, 31 years after the fall of the Berlin Wall, Polish President Andrzej Duda signed the Polish Senate’s ratification bill of the U.S.-Polish Enhanced Defense Cooperation Agreement (EDCA). This agreement contains a number of provisions that will facilitate greater defense cooperation between the United States and Poland and improve deterrence and battle readiness for NATO along the alliance’s Eastern Flank. For the Baltics, this ratification is welcome news, as it not only improves the regional deterrent posture, but also a number of crucial conditions in Poland to enable more rapid and effective defense in the event of Russian aggression on their territory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moving the Front Lines: Could Recent Moves in Europe Signal an Adjustment of U.S. Focus Eastward?</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/moving_the_front_lines/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/moving_the_front_lines/</guid>
      <description>In June the Trump administration announced its decision to pull 9,500 U.S. troops from Germany. The move was lambasted by those on the left and right alike, and indeed, at face value, it appeared counterintuitive. Any return to the Obama and Bush-era troop drawdown in Europe would be foolish facing a revisionist Russia. But if there is anything the keen and impartial observer should know by now about this administration, it is that it keeps its cards close to the chest, absorbing the criticism that inevitably comes and only revealing its end game down the line.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spring Storm Exercises Demonstrate Ongoing Commitment to Deterrence, Readiness</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/spring_storm/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/spring_storm/</guid>
      <description>Each year, Estonia hosts Spring Storm (Kevadtorm), bringing together forces from all across NATO to conduct field and live-fire exercises. Though smaller in scale and participation due to the coronavirus pandemic, this year’s exercises concluded successfully last week. Spring Storm demonstrates Estonia and its allies’ commitment to ensuring readiness in case of attack, contributing to the credibility of NATO’s deterrence posture on the Eastern Flank.
Military exercises are crucial for training and readiness purposes, as new conscripts/recruits and reservists have an opportunity to train alongside active duty personnel.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Javelin Deliveries and the Prospects of Tank Warfare in the Baltics</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/tank_warfare_baltics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/tank_warfare_baltics/</guid>
      <description>At the beginning of this month, the U.S. delivered 128 javelin anti-tank missiles to Estonia, part of ongoing cooperation between the two countries. This will provide another moderate boost to the credibility of Estonia’s deterrent posture. These kinds of smaller procurements are an important part of the broader effort to build up a credible defense in case of Russian aggression and to signal that the risk outweighs the reward for attacking the Baltic States.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Three Seas Initiative</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/three_seas_initiative/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/three_seas_initiative/</guid>
      <description>Last month, U.S. Secretary of State Mike Pompeo announced that the United States would commit up to $1 Billion in support for the Three Seas Initiative. In so doing, Congress and the administration are providing much needed assistance toward developing the economic and security infrastructure in Central and Eastern Europe. This initiative, launched in 2015 by the Polish and Croatian presidents, aims to make Central Europe a “backbone of European resilience,” in the words of Croatian President Kolinda Grabar-Kitarović.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is Baltic Security Important for the U.S., NATO, and Europe? Absolutely!</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/is_baltic_security_important/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/is_baltic_security_important/</guid>
      <description>The three Baltic States are key members of the NATO defensive alliance. Since regaining independence after the illegal Soviet occupation, Latvia, Lithuania, and Estonia have all become deeply integrated into Western institutions, such as NATO and the EU. These small countries, understanding the potential peril of reoccupation by a resurgent Russia after the annexation of Crimea, have been extremely vocal in sounding the alarm that Russia remains a security threat. They understand that the West must get serious about security lest its more vulnerable members once more get trampled.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
