<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mobility on Baltic Security Foundation</title>
    <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/categories/mobility/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Mobility on Baltic Security Foundation</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://balticsecurity.eu/categories/mobility/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Transatlantic Security Exchange 2022</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/transatlantic_security_exchange_2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/transatlantic_security_exchange_2022/</guid>
      <description>On October 6, 2022, the State Secretary of Latvian Ministry of Defense Jānis Garisons visited the Bush School of Government and Public Service at Texas A&amp;amp;M and met with Professor Gabriela Marin Thornton and her students who research Baltic security in their capstone course. The capstone course participants partner with the Baltic Security Foundation to propose ways to increase Baltic resilience with a focus on Latvia. The meeting presented an opportunity to discuss the preliminary findings and compare the perspectives on the most important regional security issues in the Baltic Sea Region.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transatlantic Security Exchange</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/transatlantic_security_exchange/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/transatlantic_security_exchange/</guid>
      <description>The Baltic Security Foundation has launched the Transatlantic Security Exchange. The program brings together experts and researchers from Europe and America to focus on further studies of Baltic security in regional and international context.
This week, the BSF team welcomed Rebekkah Chatham and Travis Andrews from the Texas A&amp;amp;M University Bush School of Government &amp;amp; Public Service who will visit several Baltic Sea states for their research on NATO, influence of Russia and China in Europe, regional military cooperation and food security.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Texas A&amp;M University Students Participate in BSF Young Leaders Mobility Program</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/texas_atm_mobility_program/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/texas_atm_mobility_program/</guid>
      <description>In October 2019, Baltic Security Foundation hosted Master of International Affairs students from Texas A&amp;amp;M University’s Bush School of Government and Public Service for the Young Leaders Mobility Program in Rīga. The students were led by Dr. Gabriela Marin-Thornton.
While on the program, the students had the opportunity to visit the Latvian Ministry of Foreign Affairs and Parliament, and participated in the Rīga Conference, organized by the Latvian MFA, MoD, and Latvian Transatlantic Organisation.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
