<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Geopolitics on Baltic Security Foundation</title>
    <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/categories/geopolitics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Geopolitics on Baltic Security Foundation</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://balticsecurity.eu/categories/geopolitics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Lithuania-Kaliningrad Transit Row: A Broader EU and NATO Perspective</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/lithuania_kaliningrad/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/lithuania_kaliningrad/</guid>
      <description>Through much of the end of June, Lithuania has been embroiled in a row with Russia over the implementation of EU sanctions on certain kinds of goods in transit between Russia and its Kaliningrad exclave.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Russia Testing Western Resolve: How will the West Respond?</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/russia_testing_western_resolve/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/russia_testing_western_resolve/</guid>
      <description>From the Baltics, to Poland, to Ukraine, and even outer space, Russia has recently been testing Western resolve on numerous fronts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Belarusian Migrant Crisis in Broader Geopolitical Context</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/belarusian_migrant_crisis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/belarusian_migrant_crisis/</guid>
      <description>For about the last two months, Lithuania has been in the throes of a migration crisis like it has never seen before.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ukraine in the Balance. Again.</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/ukraine_in_the_balance/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/ukraine_in_the_balance/</guid>
      <description>Introduction
Once again, Ukraine faces the threat of Russian aggression. Surrounded on nearly all sides, it faces a potential crisis of existence, as Moscow sees an opportunity to take on yet more ambitious objectives against its hapless neighbor.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>U.S. Perspectives on Nord Stream 2</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/perspectives_nord_stream2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/perspectives_nord_stream2/</guid>
      <description>U.S. President Joe Biden has claimed that Nord Stream 2, the controversial Russo-German pipeline project, is a “bad deal for Europe” and has stated his administration’s opposition to the project.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>As Belarus Descends into Turmoil, the West Should Bolster its Readiness</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/as_belarus_descends/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/as_belarus_descends/</guid>
      <description>Belarus seldom registers in the international press during normal times, but while years like 2020 are not so unprecedented, this certainly is not a normal year.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Future of Belarus?</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/the_future_of_belarus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/the_future_of_belarus/</guid>
      <description>The Belarusian elections occurred last Sunday, August 9th, and pitted incumbent president Alexander Lukashenko against political outsider Svetlana Tikhanovskaya.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Military Exercises in Kaliningrad Highlight Maritime Threats</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/military_exercises_in_kaliningrad_highlight_maritime_threats/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/military_exercises_in_kaliningrad_highlight_maritime_threats/</guid>
      <description>For eight or nine days beginning on April 20th, around the same time that NATO and Estonian forces were holding the Spring Storm Exercises, Russia held exercises of its own in the Kaliningrad Oblast’.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Javelin Deliveries and the Prospects of Tank Warfare in the Baltics</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/tank_warfare_baltics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/tank_warfare_baltics/</guid>
      <description>At the beginning of this month, the U.S. delivered 128 javelin anti-tank missiles to Estonia, part of ongoing cooperation between the two countries.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Belarus: An Overlooked Key to Baltic Security </title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/belarus_an_overlooked_key/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/belarus_an_overlooked_key/</guid>
      <description>Winston Churchill once famously quipped that “Russia is a riddle wrapped in a mystery inside an enigma”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Stopping Nord Stream 2 Matters for the Baltics</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/stopping_nord_stream/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/stopping_nord_stream/</guid>
      <description>Nord Stream 2 is a Russian gas pipeline project running mostly parallel to the current Nord Stream pipeline from Vyborg to Greifswald, Germany.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is Baltic Security Important for the U.S., NATO, and Europe? Absolutely!</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/is_baltic_security_important/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/is_baltic_security_important/</guid>
      <description>The three Baltic States are key members of the NATO defensive alliance.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
