<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Energy on Baltic Security Foundation</title>
    <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/tags/energy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Energy on Baltic Security Foundation</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://balticsecurity.eu/tags/energy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Securing Energy Supply in the Baltics</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/securing_energy_supply_baltics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/securing_energy_supply_baltics/</guid>
      <description>This month, Lithuania announced the arrival of a 164-tonne transformer as part of the ongoing process for synchronization with the Continental European power grid. This step is considered crucial for successfully exiting the Soviet era BRELL agreement, in which the Baltics’ power grids are controlled by Moscow. Exiting BRELL is a major component of the Baltics’ overall strategy not only for energy security, but for their national security broadly.
Under the BRELL agreement, the Baltics have been synchronously connected to the Integrated Power System/United Power System (IPS/UPS) grid with Russia and Belarus since the end of the Soviet period.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ukraine-Baltic Energy Cooperation in the Context of Russian Hybrid Aggression</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/ukraine_baltic_energy_cooperation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/ukraine_baltic_energy_cooperation/</guid>
      <description>This article provided by our Ukrainian partners, Ad Astra
Despite being different in so many aspects, Ukraine and the Baltic states have always had a lot of things in common, the main one being a troublesome neighbor on the eastern border that we all have to deal with.
The dissolution of the Soviet Union opened a new era in Russian foreign policy towards the territories that are or were once perceived as a part of the sphere of influence of the former geopolitical empire.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Stopping Nord Stream 2 Matters for the Baltics</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/stopping_nord_stream/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/stopping_nord_stream/</guid>
      <description>Nord Stream 2 is a Russian gas pipeline project running mostly parallel to the current Nord Stream pipeline from Vyborg to Greifswald, Germany. This second line would allow for additional gas flows directly from Russia to Western Europe up to a potential 110 billion cubic meters annually. At face value, this expansion is an economic opportunity that makes sense for Germany and other potential Western European customers. In a perfect world, it would be just that.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
