<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ukraine on Baltic Security Foundation</title>
    <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/tags/ukraine/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ukraine on Baltic Security Foundation</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://balticsecurity.eu/tags/ukraine/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Continued support to Ukrainians</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/ukraine_support/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/ukraine_support/</guid>
      <description>The Baltic Security Foundation continues to support Ukrainian refugees in Latvia and the civilians in Ukraine. First of all, our team member Andreis Purim has been personally involved to facilitate the delivery of humanitarian aid to Lviv, Ukraine.
Furthermore, since summer of 2022, the Baltic Security Foundation has gathered support from the U.S. Embassy in Latvia and many non-governmental organizations and individual supporters to provide free English classes for the Ukrainian refugees who have fled the Russian aggression.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Major Russian Invasion of Ukraine Imminent</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/major_russian_invasion_of_ukraine_imminent/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/major_russian_invasion_of_ukraine_imminent/</guid>
      <description>Russia will invade Ukraine. It is no longer a matter of if, but when. Some pundits have been quick to point out that Russia already invaded Ukraine in 2014 and has been an occupier since then. This is true, but short of inventing some other barbarically cumbersome turn of phrase or vague milquetoast nonsense that fails to capture the urgency of the situation, an invasion is perhaps the best word available to describe what is on the horizon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ukraine in the Balance. Again.</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/ukraine_in_the_balance/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/ukraine_in_the_balance/</guid>
      <description>Once again, Ukraine faces the threat of Russian aggression. Surrounded on nearly all sides, it faces a potential crisis of existence, as Moscow sees an opportunity to take on yet more ambitious objectives against its hapless neighbor. Unfortunately for Ukraine, nothing guarantees its security, and it is grossly, obscenely outmatched by its adversary. What exactly Russia intends to do remains a mystery, but one thing is clear: Russia plans to attack Ukraine.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
