<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>EU on Baltic Security Foundation</title>
    <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/tags/eu/</link>
    <description>Recent content in EU on Baltic Security Foundation</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://balticsecurity.eu/tags/eu/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Transatlantic response to China</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/transatlantic_response_to_china/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/transatlantic_response_to_china/</guid>
      <description>Roger W. Robinson Jr. speaks on the Transatlantic response to China, importance of the capital markets, and the international security context relevant to the Baltic Sea region.
This address is part of the Baltic Sea Security Conference 2022: Transatlantic Response to China&amp;rsquo;s Presence in the Baltic Sea Region. The conference was hosted by the Baltic Security Foundation at the Hotel Kempinski Adlon in Berlin on August 17, 2022.
The conference showcased the research on China&amp;rsquo;s presence in the Baltic Sea region domains of finance, education and infrastructure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baltic Sea Security Conference 2022</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/baltic_sea_security_conference_2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/baltic_sea_security_conference_2022/</guid>
      <description>Transatlantic response to China’s presence in the Baltic Sea Region
The Euroatlantic states sharing the Baltic Sea have been subject to persistent security threats that have made them seek international solutions to maintain peace and stability. Challenges associated with Russia have been at the forefront for decades and are so today with its war against Ukraine. Meanwhile over the last decade the regional presence of China has increased - welcomed by many but analyzed by few.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lithuania-Kaliningrad Transit Row: A Broader EU and NATO Perspective</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/lithuania_kaliningrad/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/lithuania_kaliningrad/</guid>
      <description>Through much of the end of June, Lithuania has been embroiled in a row with Russia over the implementation of EU sanctions on certain kinds of goods in transit between Russia and its Kaliningrad exclave. Russia has claimed that Lithuania’s actions are a “violation of everything,” and has promised a response that is “not diplomatic.” In turn, Lithuania has argued that it is simply putting into practice the EU sanctions regime agreed upon as early as March, and that contrary to Russian claims, its actions will not halt all transit between Russia and Kaliningrad; rather, it will only stop the flow of sanctioned goods.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baltic Cyber Resilience Report Published</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/baltic-cyber-resilience-report/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/baltic-cyber-resilience-report/</guid>
      <description>Baltic Security Foundation is proud to announce the publication of the Baltic Cyber Resilience Report. This report includes the assessment of cybersecurity issues in the three Baltic states, looking at the most important regional, bilateral and multilateral levels. This publication was made possible with the support of Microsoft NV and Mr. Uldis Šalajevs.
To access the full report, click here</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baltic Sea Security Initiative Report Published by Jamestown Foundation</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/baltic-sea-security-initiative-report/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/baltic-sea-security-initiative-report/</guid>
      <description>Baltic Security Foundation is proud to annouce the publication of the Baltic Sea Security Initiative Report in conjunction with the Jamestown Foundation (Washington, D.C.). The report is the product of cooperative research conducted between 2019-2020 with a number of regional security experts from throughout the Baltic Sea Region, providing both assessments and recommendations for policy makers in the fields of defense and deterrence, societal security, energy security, and more. Click the link below to access the full report.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Belarusian Migrant Crisis in Broader Geopolitical Context</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/belarusian_migrant_crisis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/belarusian_migrant_crisis/</guid>
      <description>For about the last two months, Lithuania has been in the throes of a migration crisis like it has never seen before. In retaliation to the sanctions placed on his regime following the forced grounding of a passenger airliner to arrest journalist Roman Protasevich, Belarusian President Aleksandr Lukashenka promised to force Europe (and in particular, Lithuania) to deal with drug smuggling and migrant flows on their own. Aside from Lukashenka’s claim to have been stopping migrants and smugglers in the past, the statement gives clear indication of intent to weaponize migration and the flow of contraband.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Future of Belarus?</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/the_future_of_belarus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/the_future_of_belarus/</guid>
      <description>The Belarusian elections occurred last Sunday, August 9th, and pitted incumbent president Alexander Lukashenko against political outsider Svetlana Tikhanovskaya. For what was supposed to be another easy campaign in Lukashenko’s winning streak, the protests leading up, and following the elections have sparked internal turmoil in Belarus.
The Belarusian government now faces its biggest crisis in 26 years, as protests and police violence sweep the capital and the opposition increases their demands.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Three Seas Initiative</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/three_seas_initiative/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/three_seas_initiative/</guid>
      <description>Last month, U.S. Secretary of State Mike Pompeo announced that the United States would commit up to $1 Billion in support for the Three Seas Initiative. In so doing, Congress and the administration are providing much needed assistance toward developing the economic and security infrastructure in Central and Eastern Europe. This initiative, launched in 2015 by the Polish and Croatian presidents, aims to make Central Europe a “backbone of European resilience,” in the words of Croatian President Kolinda Grabar-Kitarović.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Defending the Suwałki Gap</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/defending_suwalki_gap/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/defending_suwalki_gap/</guid>
      <description>At the end of last month, Lithuania and Poland announced that the two countries would each assign a brigade to NATO Headquarters in Poland to “train and act together” for the defense of the Suwałki Gap. According to the signed act of affiliation, Lithuania’s Iron Wolf Mechanized Brigade and Poland’s 15th Mechanized Brigade will train jointly to prepare for operations in the Gap, though they will remain under their own national command.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baltic Fund</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/baltic_fund/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/baltic_fund/</guid>
      <description>On November 28, 2019, Baltic Security Foundation team participated in the NATO Eastern Flank Security conference, hosted by Warsaw Institute. Following a keynote speech by Piotr Naimski, Secretary of State in the Chancellery of the Prime Minister of Poland, Government Plenipotentiary for Strategic Energy Infrastructure, Mr Olevs Nikers spoke at the panel on energy security, covering political and economic issues of nuclear power and natural gas, while Mr Otto Tabuns gave his views on intraregional and European challenges for Baltic security at the discussion on defence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baltic Sea Security Initiative</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/baltic_sea_security_initiative/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/baltic_sea_security_initiative/</guid>
      <description>BSSI gathers Baltic Sea region experts to assess and recommend better solutions in the fields of defence, societal security, economic security and cybersecurity. The experts look at what the countries of Northern, Eastern and Central Europe can do more efficiently together to achieve stronger regional security. The initiative consists of eight workshops in the Baltic Sea countries (Estonia, Latvia, Lithuania, Poland, Germany, Denmark etc.). The main conclusions of the initiative will be publicly presented and discussed in a conference in Helsinki, Finland in the Spring 2020.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Belarus: An Overlooked Key to Baltic Security</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/belarus_an_overlooked_key/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/belarus_an_overlooked_key/</guid>
      <description>Winston Churchill once famously quipped that “Russia is a riddle wrapped in a mystery inside an enigma”. A keen observer will notice that Alyaksandar Lukashenka’s Belarus is much the same. All too often, Western analysts have made the mistake of grossly oversimplifying Belarus’ relationship with Russia, as well as its domestic political affairs and broader foreign policy. This has led the West to neglect relations with Minsk, where despite a less than ideal government, great strategic opportunity lies, and where there is also significant strategic risk.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regional Activities 2019</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/regional_activities/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/regional_activities/</guid>
      <description>October 2019 has been busy for the Baltic Security Foundation, pursuing our goal of fostering and promoting Baltic defense and security. The team has both participated in and organized events covering regional security issues.
The Rīga Conference 2019 took place on October 11th and 12th. Mr. Olevs Nikers and Mr. Otto Tabuns were both invited to participate. The agenda included current challenges, such as the issue of EU and NATO identities as well as understanding European strategic autonomy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baltic Security Foundation Presents at the ECPR General Conference in Wrocław</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/wroclaw_conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/wroclaw_conference/</guid>
      <description>BSF President Mr. Olevs Nikers and BSF Director Mr. Otto Tabuns took part in the panel “Addressing Security Challenges in the Baltic Region through Multilateral Cooperation” of the European Consortium for Political Research (ECPR) 13th General Conference September 5, 2019 in Wrocław, Poland.
During his presentation “Sub-Regional Defense Synchronization – Theory Perspectives and Security Expectations for the Baltics,” Mr. Nikers outlined and discussed the origin and sustainability of the modern security alliance between small countries.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is Baltic Security Important for the U.S., NATO, and Europe? Absolutely!</title>
      <link>https://balticsecurity.eu/is_baltic_security_important/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://balticsecurity.eu/is_baltic_security_important/</guid>
      <description>The three Baltic States are key members of the NATO defensive alliance. Since regaining independence after the illegal Soviet occupation, Latvia, Lithuania, and Estonia have all become deeply integrated into Western institutions, such as NATO and the EU. These small countries, understanding the potential peril of reoccupation by a resurgent Russia after the annexation of Crimea, have been extremely vocal in sounding the alarm that Russia remains a security threat. They understand that the West must get serious about security lest its more vulnerable members once more get trampled.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
